[Music]
so we're looking at
uh
right looking at multiarm banded
problems
right so you looked at a couple of ways
of solving it so essentially you try to
keep an estimate of the value function
around right the value function is the
expected payoff that you get for pulling
an arm right you keep an estimate of the
value function around and then you
behave
um some explorative fashion with respect
to that value function that you have
right so either you do Epsilon 3D or you
do soft Max or something and uh you get
some kind of asymptotic guarantees
correct
yes okay good
um we also spoke about other forms of
optimality so one of them we spoke about
was regret optimality so regret
optimality is
what reducing the total I mean or
increasing the total reward that you get
over the process of
learning right so so the initial loss
that you get due
to the EXP the exploration you want to
minimize so that I come as close as
possible to the optimal case as quickly
as possible right so that is essentially
what regret is all about and so we'll
start by looking at uh one algorithm
which in some sense has become uh the
popular most popular uh Bandit algorithm
around right now uh because it's so easy
to implement and also gives you not too
bad regret bonds okay it's called
the upper confidence Bond
the upper confidence Bond algorithm or
the UCB algorithm okay so I'll use
slightly different notation today right
uh not not too different I'll try to as
much as possible uh I'll try to
translate on the Fly okay to the
notation that is used in the textbook
right so even though I we will give we
will be giving you some papers to read
uh you can take care of linking the UCB
paper and the B elimination paper and
other things right on mod we'll be
giving you some papers to read and the
notation in the papers will be very
different okay you probably have to
spend like half an hour just uh trying
to understand the notation but when I'm
explaining it in class to the extent
possible I'll try to map it to the
notations used in the book right so that
you have one uniform set of things that
you can keep track off throughout right
the changes are the following right I'm
going to assume that there
are capital K arms right so earlier I
was assuming there were n arms but it
turns out the reason I want to change n
is uh we're going to now talk about a
notion of time right so now so there are
going to be pulls at every time instant
and so on so forth
and uh this should be familiar to
electrical engineers so if time is
discrete you denote it by n okay if time
is continuous denoted by T right so I
want to be able to denote discrete time
so I want to use n for discrete time
okay and so we'll save n for discrete
time and I'll not use that for the
number of arms so that's the reason I
switch to
K
okay assume there are K arms and uh so
as before with each arm there is
associated some
arbitrary probability distribution which
I don't know right whenever I pull an
arm I'll get a sample drawn from that
probability distribution it could be
veroli it could be goian right it could
be poison we don't know what
distribution it is but according to that
distribution we'll get
a payoff right and what else do we did
we assume last
time that there is the expectation given
for that distribution right yeah yeah we
assume that the distribution is
stationary it's not going to change with
time right and that there is an
expectation associated with that
distribution which you denote by Q qar
of a right when you say qar of a it is
the the expectation for pulling arm a
okay this
clear so here is the UCB algorithm so
assume there are K arms so the
initialization phase is
play each arm at least once play each
arm once right you have to pull every
arm at least one time you can't do
better than that agreed if if I never
pull the arm I don't know anything about
that arms right so I need to pull each
arm at least once so that's the least so
we start off with that and then we do
the following in a loop
so you remember what QJ is
is estimated payoff expected payoff
right so this is average reward that
we'll be maintaining right that's a
value function right for RJ so QJ is the
estimate that I have at
time n right QJ is estimate I have a
Time n for MJ so essentially what I'm
doing is I'm taking whatever is the
current estimate right and I'm adding
this expression to
that right
and then I'm playing the arm that gives
me the highest value for this total
expression right so the way to think
about this is the
following I'll come back to this we'll
show things more precisely later
but let's assume that this is
my Q of
om1 right whatever is some some scale
this the the x-axis I mean the x axis
let us assume is the arm index and the y
axis is the expected payoff right so
that is
q1 then I have
Q2 say
Q3 and
Q4 let's say I have four arms right so
what the idea behind upper confidence
bond is to say that hey I'm not going to
use just the estimated expectation so
far
right so I've actually drawn many
samples right I can use the samples that
I have drawn so far to figure out what
is the confidence with which I can say
that this is the
expectation right so so you can you can
think of giving kind some kind of a
bound around this you can say that okay
this is the expectation I
have right but the true value of q1 or
qar one right the Q value of qar one is
going to lie within that
band right so intuitively you can see
that the more number of times I have
sampled arm one the smaller is this
going to
be right if I taken a lot of samples
then I'm more confident about the
expectation that I'm going to tell you
right we know that as the number of
samples tends to Infinity I this q q
will converge to qar so we know that
right q1 will converge to qar 1 if the
number of times have sampled one goes to
Infinity so the more the number of
samples I draw the narrower will be this
band of
uncertainty right so likewise I'll have
a band like this
for Q2 right I'll have a band like this
for Q3 I'll have a band like this for Q4
so what arm do you am I suggesting that
you take now
no I'm I'm saying take I'm one that's
what essentially UCB tell
here right so why do you think this kind
of a scenario might have happened I
might have chosen arm for a lot of times
because it seems to have a higher value
so my uncertainty and the value of arm
four has come down all lot right but arm
one I have not taken enough times arm
three obviously I not taken enough times
but I'm really not inclined to take arm
three anymore because
given my current state of
uncertainty right the probability that
arm three will be higher
than this end right I mean it's very
very small right even though my
uncertainty arm three is very high I'm
not inclined to take that arm because
the chance that it will truly be
high the chance that it will truly be
high is very
small right while for arm one the chance
that it might be better than arm four
it's fairly decent so this interval I'm
telling you is some kind of bound that
says that with very high probability
right the true value of q1 will lie
within this bond that means there is a
chance that it will lie here which case
it can be higher than
Q4 right so I'll take this if I take
this a few more times and let us say
after some time my estimate moves up
like this but my
estimate moves up a little bit but my
bounds also shrink right now it might
not look attractive compared to Q4 so
I'll go back to
taking
Q4 right so that's why you can see in
this expression I have the total number
of samples I have drawn of MJ right what
NJ is number of times I have trans
sampled arm J so the larger the
NJ the smaller this expression is going
to
become okay so larger the number of
samples I draw the smaller this
expression will become and therefore
this interval will keep coming down
okay what's that yeah that's more like a
normalizing term right it is there in
all the Expressions all the values right
all the intervals that you compute so
it's not relatively it is not going to
matter but you'll need it to show some
results later so so algorithm itself
very
clear right so the things here the N is
essentially the number of times I have
played arm so far any arm NJ is the
number of times I played arj
okay so you have that pictorial
description of what this algorithm is
doing great so what is nice about this
algorithm it's very very simple
algorithm you saw that right there's
nothing about it all you need to do is
apart from keeping track of QJ you have
to keep track
of NJ as well which you are anyway doing
if you are doing that incremental
update right if you remember last class
we wrote the incremental update so the
step size was anywhere related to NJ so
the only additional overhead would be if
you had been using a constant Alpha for
your updates you'll have to remember NJ
and addition otherwise it's exactly the
same thing like we did for Epsilon gring
so instead of randomly deciding which
action to take for exploration
you you don't do any exploration also
the random the random number generator
also is gone now right this is very
deterministic
algorithm right so what is so great
about it yeah so don't we need some kind
of normalizing on QJ
no because the other term might be a
very small term even when Q might be a
very large value doesn't
matter why does it matter like the like
you like the expected pay offs can be
something like 10 ah that way okay fine
fine fine fine fine uh yeah so all of
this this this particular form of
expression does assume that the rewards
are bonded between 0o and
one right so yeah I'll come to that in a
minute so yeah you right so you can
rescale the rewards if you want to right
as long as all the rewards are positive
so you can rescale them to lie between
zero and one but if you have negative
rewards you'll have to think about how
we want to do this okay
[Music]
[Applause]